Chinese banks are now trapped, and it
has forced China to enter an era of
full-blown extend and pretend. Now,
they've been on the edge of it for quite
some time, as we've been talking about,
but recent data and information has
shown they've crossed that critical
threshold into the low-rate trap,
squeezing profitability and bleeding
cash. So, the recent confirmation we got
from the People's Bank of China on
pretty grim lending statistics, just
more confirmation that trap has indeed
been sprung.
We're seeing more reports, even in the
mainstream media, how lenders in China
are now reaching out to struggling
borrowers, and there are a lot of them,
with the number growing all the time,
offering payment holidays and other
creative ways to avoid default and
foreclosure. And with so many Chinese
properties underwater, foreclosing on a
property means the bank only has bad
options. Either sell the thing and take
the loss, which they're not going to do,
especially with Beijing breathing down
everyone's neck, and then the only other
option is to take the house and become
the owner, which means the bank, while,
you know, okay, they avoid taking a
loss, but now they're going to bleed
even more cash, having to pay for
upkeep, or even getting it ready to be
able to rent it. So, not wanting to do
either of those, the Chinese are taking
a page out of Wall Street's handbook and
modifying loans on the fly. Rather than
force a sale or have to become
responsible for a property, just find
some way, any way, to keep the current
owner in the house and hope someday it
all just works out. And this should
sound way too familiar.
And just to show you what I mean, for
the first 3 months of this year, new
household loans in China were basically
zero. Zero. In the same 3 months of last
year, it was roughly a trillion. So,
from a trillion to zero. Banks are
getting squeezed. They're bleeding cash.
So, in that situation,
the only thing left is to get creative.
To start with, there's a huge difference
between what China's banks report as
profits and their operating cash flow.
And even then, profitability within the
banking sector has been declining for
years. Now, people are told we're all
told lower rates are stimulus. They're
not. While they might encourage a couple
borrowers to borrow a little more, it's
only under the right circumstances. And
even then, falling interest rates do
nothing for lenders. Unless deposit
costs fall as much or more than loan
rates do, bank profits are going to get
squeezed. And then there's another
problem, the asset mix. Economic growth
in China has fallen off sharply over the
last, let's call it, 8 years. And the
property bust really took off here in
the 2020s. So, quite naturally, banks
and other financial firms have been
avoiding riskier loan opportunities,
choosing instead safety, government
bonds, the highest quality borrowers,
and the like. The lowest return types of
assets. But as more and more banks buy
safety, the rate of return falls
farther. It falls faster than any
decline in funding costs. So, the more
China wants to own safety, the less
profitable its banking sector can be,
particularly with no other way to
generate higher returns somewhere else
in the economy. Or like Japan did, take
the money that they've got overseas
after converting it into euro dollars
first. Basically, the Chinese are stuck,
which is just what was reported by some
of the biggest firms at the end of the
first quarter 2026. Quote, "Three of
China's largest banks reported nearly
flat annual profits on Friday as the
world's second largest economy reels
from a deepening property sector debt
crisis amid a prolonged slowdown.
Industrial and Commercial Bank of China,
the world's largest lender by assets,
and China Construction Bank, both
reported less than 1% growth in 2025 net
profit." And those numbers are
artificial. China has yet to see the
property crisis bottom out as house
prices slip across the country and large
so-called zombie developers, or
developers that are unprofitable,
continue to just roll over loans.
However, net interest margins, a gauge
of profitability, have remained steady.
Before we go on with our video today,
let me ask you a question. What if your
gold could actually pay you every single
month in more gold? That's what today's
video sponsor, Monetary Metals, lets you
do.
And here's how it works. You still own
the gold, it's still in your name, it's
fully insured, but instead of just
sitting there doing nothing, it actually
starts working for you. Monetary Metals
has built a system that turns idle gold
into productive gold, earning real yield
paid in physical gold, not dollars. No
selling, no trading, no converting. You
keep your gold, and every month you get
more of it. It's a simple idea, but it
solves a big problem. If gold is money,
it should act like money. And now it
finally can.
If you're a long-term gold holder
looking for a smarter way to store
value, check them out at
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
Again, that's
I highly recommend booking a call with
them today to see if they're the right
fit for you. We thank Monetary Metals
for their sponsorship, and now let's get
back to the rest of our video.
Well, net interest margins have been
steady for over a year because bond
yields bottomed out in ultra-low
territory during 2025. More recently,
though, we've seen Chinese rates begin
to creep back down again to the point
China's bond curve right now is bull
steepening. That's not a good sign for
anything, including Chinese bank
profitability. The 10-year bond rate was
at 1.79 today for the first time since
November, but just as important, look
what's been happening at the front of
the yield curve. The 2-year yield is
moving up and down as it usually does
this time of year, but the 1-year rate,
that one has dipped below 1.2% for the
first time since January 2025.
That's not a good sign for China,
Chinese banks, for interest rates, or
anything that we're going to talk about
here. So, put the lack of profitability
within this interest rate environment
together with the lack of lending
opportunities either in the property
sector or certainly in the real economy,
and what it means is that Chinese banks
only want to lend to a smaller and
smaller group of borrowers who will pay
them less and less when they do. This is
why bank profitability is at a historic
low, and it's not getting any better.
China's yield curve says it may actually
get worse.
So, that's already one huge problem.
Lack of profitability on the loans that
China's banks are actually willing to
make when they're actually willing to
make a few loans. But, then there's
another problem, maybe even the bigger
problem, the hidden real estate bust
problem.
The potential losses on those they did
make years ago. By all accounts, the
official reports anyway, loan losses are
minimal. Official non-performing loan
rates are nothing big, but
hardly anyone believes the numbers they
put out in public, especially with
little profitability as a cushion. You
know, you take any kind of significant
hit from bad loans, and it quickly
erodes current profits and causes
whichever bank is doing it to have to
dip into its loan loss reserves, and
maybe even therefore threaten that same
bank's equity. I mean, this is one
reason why China's government had
proposed a bank recapitalization plan,
remember that? Way back in September
2024 with that whole bazooka fiasco. By
adding government equity, Beijing would
increase the margins that at least the
biggest banks would have so that they
could start taking maybe more realistic
losses to begin cleaning up this massive
mess. Because right now, Chinese banking
sector is doing almost nothing for the
real economy as we'll see in just a
minute. The only way to get everything
moving again would be to inject
government money, telling the system,
the central authority would be taking
most of the hit via the biggest banks.
So, there's going to be a second round
of this recapitalization carried out
this month. There was a first round last
year where about 300 billion yuan or
roughly 44 billion dollars equivalent in
government bonds will be issued with the
proceeds going to some of China's
largest state-owned banks. Now, Beijing,
they already did it last year injecting
a similar amount into four of the top
six.
And you can see how well that worked.
And yes, that is sarcasm. Because what's
the point? They did the recapitalization
plan just like they did the bazooka, and
what did it get them? As far as China's
banks are concerned,
banks aren't doing anything. They got
maybe some bigger numbers for equity
capital on some of the biggest banks,
but it didn't do anything for the
banking sector overall to get it moving
again nor the real economy. So, it's
stimulus that once again doesn't
actually stimulate. You have to ask a
question why that is. What is the real
problem here or set of problems that
become so interlocking intractable, none
of these big huge bazookas even move the
needle.
So, we have no idea what the possible
loan losses might be, but the fact the
recapitalization plan isn't working and
it's not leading to anything positive
already tells you the scale of the
possible losses is probably bigger than
anyone in China is willing to admit at
least publicly. But, we don't need them
to.
The bank data, which I'll get to, plus
the changing behavior of banks is all
the evidence we need. As I said in the
intro, the era of full-blown extend and
pretend is upon China. Quote, "Several
state-owned banks have approached
cash-strapped borrowers and offered them
payment holidays. Payment holidays on
their mortgages for as long as two
years, according to people familiar with
the matter who asked not to be
identified discussing their firm's
policies. Some lenders are working with
individual customers to find buyers for
their homes instead of calling defaults
and foreclosing on the properties, the
people said. Local courts across the
country have slowed the pace of
accepting cases involving defaulted
mortgages to limit the volume of forced
property sales according to these same
people. Some courts have even suspended
or limited the number of litigation
cases that banks can file for
residential mortgage defaults. And the
moves, they underscore how China's local
institutions are working to limit the
damage of a years-long property crisis
that shows no signs of coming to an end.
They also raise the of whether official
non-performing mortgage ratios, which
have persistently stayed around 1% for
big banks despite rising defaults, only
hint at the true scale of the problem.
And that last part should be completely
obvious. You can't trust official bad
loan estimates. If they were in reality
what those figures claim, China's banks
would be booming. They'd be lending
everywhere, and interest rates on
government bonds and everything else
would be rising because no one would
want to own low-yielding, boring, safe,
and liquid. Everything, and I mean
everything, points to those estimates as
being heavily managed, if not outright
manufactured. And what Bloomberg is now
reporting with these increasingly
creative loan modifications, that's all
the proof any honest person will need.
This is the trap. This is the trap
leading to full-blown extend and
pretend. Now, since home values have
been declining for years, borrowers
increasingly don't have any positive
equity. They're upside down, which is a
condition and a term we here in the US
got to be entirely too familiar with
about 17 years ago. And when that
happens, any lender who forecloses on a
property is going to take a loss because
the property they just seized is worth
less than the loan. But if your bank's
profits are already getting squeezed,
they're going lower and lower because of
the low interest rate trap, you're not
going to want to take the loss, so you
start to do everything you can to avoid
it. And it's increasingly hard to sell
the houses anyway. Just look at the
housing market data. But even beyond
that, reported over in China, there's
less than a quarter of foreclosures that
were offered at auction actually getting
sold. Less than a quarter. So, seizing
and selling, that has already become a
less viable option to begin with. So,
maybe you foreclose, but then don't
sell. That way the loan is gone and you
have the collateral, but as far as your
books are concerned, there's no loss
yet. But the big problem with that
tactic is that while it kicks the can
down the road on taking the loss, first
of all, there's no money coming in on
the property unless the bank wants to
start being a landlord and renting it
out. And whether it does or doesn't,
there are upfront cash costs and
maintenance fees to keep it going. In
other words, foreclosure is a cash drain
unless the seized asset can be
liquidated quickly. But once again,
banks don't have the cash cushion either
because they aren't making any money on
the loans that they are making. So,
what's left for them to do? The only
thing they can do is keep the current
borrower right where they are. So, let's
go back to the article. Some banks have
reached out to borrowers who are facing
financial strain to propose solutions.
One of those, Annie G, is 36 year old
who lives in Chengdu, a southwestern
Chinese city,
said she was losing sleep last year over
her 4,500 yuan monthly mortgage
installment on a two-bedroom apartment
that she bought in 2019 for 1.4 million
yuan. G had to run a small eatery, and
when it closed, she said she couldn't
make her finances work. And after
mounting problems paying all of her
bills, she missed a mortgage payment
last year in June.
Right around the time the economy really
took a turn for the worse. To her
surprise, she received a phone call from
a Bank of China representative a month
later.
G was told she could repay only the
interest portion of her loan for as long
as two years, cutting her monthly
mortgage burden almost in half. And that
still wasn't enough. In September, the
same bank representative offered her a
six-month reprieve on both principal and
interest payments. So, for China's
banks, there's increasingly fewer
borrowers that you can lend to. And
those where you can make loans, they pay
you lower interest. Profitability falls,
cash flow is strained, and the banking
sector has little margin to clean up its
bad loans. They can't foreclose on
anything because everyone's already
underwater, and even if they did,
nothing is selling. So, banks just don't
have the cash to be landlords. Thus,
what they're left with is the era of
full-blown extend and pretend.
So, given everything we just went over,
the statistics reported by People's Bank
of China on credit, debt, and what banks
are up to over there, no surprise
whatsoever. In fact, all it really does
is confirm the trap in the extend
pretend background.
The total outstanding stock of loans in
China grew by just 5.7% in March. That's
year-over-year. Not just a new record
low, but a significant deterioration in
rate just in March alone. It was 6% in
the January-February period. So, a big
slump on top of the long-term slide. And
last March, just to give you some
reference, last March the year-over-year
change in outstanding loans was 7.4%,
and 2 years ago, it was 9.6%.
And neither of those were any good. So,
what good did all the quote-unquote
stimulus do? The bazookas, the bailouts,
the recapitalization, at least the first
half of it. Now, household loans only
increased by 280 billion yuan in March,
which was way below the nearly 1
trillion increase in March of 2025. So,
for the first quarter as a whole, 2026,
household loans were basically zero
after banks posted the biggest monthly
decline on record last month, the
previous month in February. And that
compared to just over a trillion in new
household loans in the first quarter of
2025. Now, in terms of total social
financing, new RMB loans are coming from
the banking sector. In the first
quarter, they They down almost 11%
compared to the same period a year ago
and are now so far off the previous
trend, it confirms only a new trend in
lending, which is not a good one, as
everything we've been talking about here
points to. Again, what did any of the
stimulus end up actually stimulating?
Nothing other than excited mainstream
media pieces of mainly in the West
propping up both the CCP and Keynesian
economics, neither which are ever
effective at anything related to an
economy. Instead, as we keep seeing,
banks are trapped and they aren't
getting out anytime soon, which leaves
China with only two bad options. The
first one is they can rip the band-aid
off, stop pussyfooting around, and take
their medicine. Yes, that risks turning
a a bank problem into a full-blown
crisis, maybe even liquidity crisis, but
maybe most people don't realize that's
not actually the worst-case scenario.
We've been taught and told that it is
and we need to avoid it at all costs,
but that's not actually true and our own
experience should have taught us that.
Crash case is not even close to the
worst case. A crash is bad, sure, maybe
even catastrophic, but being stuck going
nowhere for a very, very long time is
much, much worse. Time is the biggest
factor. Better to get it done and over
with rather than languish for years, for
decades, maybe even generations. Just
ask the Japanese or the Europeans or the
Americans.
Those are the only two choices. Either
get it done and over with, however
violently it might get, and get going on
a legitimate recovery, or spend the rest
of your life trying to avoid a crash by
sacrificing all the upside for as long
as you're stuck in the trap. That's
really what it is. The idea that
stimulus will help avoid the crash but
shorten the time needed to extend and
pretend. It's all false. It's backward.
History shows that's not how this works.
So, China's banks are stuck. They can't
lend. They can't make money. They can't
clean up their past indiscretions,
really Beijing's indiscretions. Because
they can't lend, the economy isn't going
to get anywhere, which means everything
in China is even further trapped with
nowhere to go but down. The losses need
to be taken. It really is that simple.
The damage has already been done. The
mistakes have already been made. They
need to be cleaned up. Rather than do it
right and risk disorder and messiness,
Chinese authorities are convinced they
just need the right stimulus and more
time to carry it out. Fake it until they
make it.
Yeah, and the Japanese said the same
thing. The right government stimulus and
more time. And they got it. Dozens of
QEs, massive government debts, couple of
generations, and what do they have to
show for it? Other than societal
self-destruction. There is a lesson
here. Don't do bubbles. But if you do do
bubbles, don't do Keynes.
We also have to keep in mind that all
this happened largely before the full
weight of the energy shock hits both
China and the rest of the world. And
it's not just the energy shock, as I
talked about yesterday's video. There's
another shock that also needs more
attention.
The video link below. As always, thank
you very much for joining me. Huge thank
you. Euro Dollar University members and
subscribers. And until next time,
take care.